" A painting is always quite moral
" when it is tragic and it gives the horror
of the things it depicts . " Barbey d 'AureviIIy .
" DeIassaIIe Boarding school "
- Monsieur DeIassaIIe ... - Yes .
- It 's about time you blew your horn . - It 's okay ...
I 'II get the things out of the car .
- Your salads are rotten ! - You aren 't paying for them .
Line up , please . And be quiet .
Oh , what a pain .
- lovely kids ! - Can 't wait for the escape .
Get out !
Do your eyes hurt , dear colleague ?
I hurt myself getting up .
You 're up early . Last night , I was doing my rounds ...
about 4 A.M. , and I heard screams coming out of your room .
The chaste woman loves to contemplate dawn , doesn 't she ?
You spent too much time with the Jesuits , M. Drain .
Everyone can 't be thrown out of the school system .
Brute !
- " Tiene , Senora . " - Thank you , darling .
Oh , it 's so nice !
We all need a vacation .
Our body needs to eliminate its toxins .
Tomorrow , mademoiselle , I 'II be all naked , and you ...
how did you plan this long weekend ?
I 'II be home , in Niort . Deux Sevres . Heard of it ?
Sous-Prefecture Maine , Bressuire and Partenay .
Getting some fresh air ?
It warms up my heart , M. Drain .
It still has the smell of the country .
A graceful instrument , but with all the rains ...
I prefer my old umbrella .
In my country , instead of your ugly black umbrella ...
you 'd wear a sombrero and ...
spend your breaks in a hammock .
It 's such a frivolous thing to give an educator .
Does your teacher really look that way , Jose ?
Yes , sir . And he used to come to school on a horse .
I 'II never get used to it .
I told him it was a horse to please him .
- It was only a mule . - Go play , JoseIito .
- What 's the matter ? - Look .
- miguel . - Of course , michel . Who else ?
- Did you have another fight ? - He came back at 3 A.M.
How have you stood him for so long ?
He wasn 't always that way .
At the beginning , he really made me happy .
It was for your money .
Why are you trying to be nasty ? Don 't you think ...
life is hard enough for us ?
I may be reactionary ...
but this is absolutely astounding .
The legal wife consoIing the mistress . No , no and no .
- What the hell are you both doing here ? - Nothing .
Nothing . Like kids . Nothing .
Come on and kiss me !
- Did you look at me ? - Are you still angry ?
What about you , Cricri , aren 't you kissing your husband ?
Let 's see ...
aren 't you supposed to be on break today ?
I told her to stay .
- Don 't you see how she looks ? - exactly . She needs air .
And her shoes . Did you see the soles ?
I 've always told her to buy heavy shoes , the real things .
A sick person shouIdn 't worry about her appearance .
- I 'm not sick . - She 's delicate , you know it
delicate ? Yes , when she came from Caracas .
Today , she 's a cute little ruin .
She doesn 't risk anything . Ruins are indestructible
She 'II bury us all . Won 't you , my little ruin ?
That 's enough . Go out and play both of you .
Yes , a black little bottle .
She smelled it like that , and it wasn 't perfume .
I can tell you , they drink .
That 's why they 're always together .
- What was in the bottle ? - Whiskey , idiot !
please , I don 't want to hear about that anymore .
Patard , if you want to spend your vacation here ...
you 'II have all the time to draw .
M. Patard , you heard .
You won 't go on vacation .
miguel , what 's the matter ?
- I didn 't want to punish him . - So don 't threaten him .
Patard did very well on his english quiz .
That 's not a reason to disgrace himself .
I won 't have any regrets .
No . I can 't . I can 't .
I wasn 't even able to get a divorce . So !
- Do you still love him ? - Of course not .
- You can 't understand . - Am I stupid ?
- Divorce is a deadly sin . - really !
And what about the knife you carried around for a month ...
- Wasn 't that a deadly sin ? - I was jealous . I was mad .
But to concoct this thing ... No .
As you wish . But think about it .
We 'II never find a better opportunity .
And we have just three days .
Everyone knows I am leaving for Niort . You 'II come and rest .
- Don 't you believe in hell ? - Not since I was seven .
I do .
- Fish again . - Not fish again .
It 's the same fish as last night .
- Make me two fried eggs . - You 're not gonna start , are you ?
I put in a liter of vinegar and a kilo of onions .
I 'm not saying it 's bad . But , you can smell that it 's fish .
It stinks .
Yes , yes , later , later .
No , thank you .
- help yourself . - I 'm not hungry .
You must set an example . My liver doesn 't allow me fat .
M. DeIassaIIe , may I ask for a glass of wine ?
- You already had two . - only one . only one .
well .
" Bonum vinum laetificat coro mini . "
- What is it ? A bone ? - I told you I wasn 't hungry .
I 'm asking you to eat .
- swallow ! - I can 't help it . I just can 't .
swallow .
- delicious fish , M. Raymond ? - Perfect . Perfect .
It seems extremely nutritious .
What these gentlemen need , is a little hard time .
Be quiet or I 'II keep you all here this weekend . swallow .
Everyone is looking at you . swallow .
- It 's disgusting . - Sorry ?
Some things are hard to swallow .
I 'm not talking about the fish .
M. Drain , throw these hooligans out of here .
What is this supposed to be ?
You 're going to eat your fish and shut up .
- I told you to throw them out . - Yes , sir .
- M . Raymond , go help your colleague . - Yes , sir .
Get out , everybody . What is this ?
Get out and be careful .
What kind of a supper is it for these growing boys ?
A slice of sausage and two spoons of mashed potatoes ?
They should 've eaten what they were served .
- In the army ... - You 're not an adjutant
- But a soup merchant . - I can 't buy coaIfish for 3000 francs .
You 'd rather make them sick .
As a kid , we used to buy whiting .
CoaIfish was too expensive .
They need expensive fish . I buy it but ...
at a price that I can afford .
It 's a mistake to buy on sale .
The fishmonger is not as stupid as we are . He knows .
It 's not his money . It 's mine .
I 'm paying for everything here .
I 'm paying for the doorkeeper . And M. Drain .
I even paid Germaine , Sabine , Therese .
I 'm paying you too , nicole . I accept it .
But when the kids are involved , it upsets me . I ...
I can 't stand it .
calm down . It 's not good for you .
I 'd Iike to die , and not see him anymore .
Die darling . Die , and do it quickly .
We 'II have a nice funeral for you , and we 'II get rid of you .
The school won 't suffer ...
and I 'II feel much better .
well , children , have fun .
I have to wake up early . I 'II go and pack .
well , so ... I 'm leaving at 7 A.M.
Have a nice vacation , darling . Take care . See you , the other one .
Have a nice vacation !
A three day honeymoon .
Oh no . Oh no .
nicole !
- nicole ! - I 'm up here . I 'm coming down .
What are you doing ?
Be careful . Move back .
Those riding the bus , raise your hands .
will your sister still be in the bathroom ?
If we get there before ten . You 'II see , I made a hole .
- Give me the pack back ! - You 'II see my sister naked .
- It 's worth a pack a cigarettes . - No ! Give them back to me !
Soudieu , aren 't you part of our group ?
No . We 'II share a cab , the four of us .
Money is pouring out of your pockets .
Don 't you have a suitcase , de Gasquet ?
The chauffeur will take it . He 's being paid for that .
Our personal chauffeurs don 't do their job right , dear friend .
Have a nice vacation , sir .
- You too - Thank you .
PIantiveau , did madame come down ?
I was ringing the bell when they drove through the gate .
- I opened it . - Both of them ?
Madame DeIassaIIe and mademoiselle Horner .
I thought you knew .
Of course , I knew . I just forgot .
Except that it 's a problem .
especially for these gentlemen .
One of you must stay to watch those on detention .
- You 'II feel funny about coming back to Niort . - Why ?
- That 's where you had troubles in high school . - troubles ...
I resigned , that 's all .
- Do you still have your parents ? - No .
I 've got a couple of teachers living on the first floor .
- What ? There are people in the house ? - I thought about it .
I thought about everything . We are not risking a thing .
You 're tired . Do you want me to drive ?
You can 't drive .
I couId never afford a car .
- This way , I cannot think . - Good . So keep driving .
Keep your nerves for tomorrow .
We 'II never have the courage .
- You don 't know me . - Yes , I know you very well .
You can wish someone 's death , but kill ...
You must 've wished my death , didn 't you ?
I didn 't . But he did . He would say to me ...
" Don 't worry . With her heart condition , it won 't take long .
" After she dies , we 'II share the school . "
It 's horrible ! Don 't you believe me ?
What did you answer ?
- Do you want me to be honest ? - Can you ?
- I didn 't know you that well ... - Don 't talk .
I 'd rather not know .
Watch the step .
mile . Horner ! What a surprise !
Don 't bother .
What a huge trunk .
It always upsets M. Herboux when I take ...
- more than a suitcase . - Good evening .
Mme. Herboux , M.A. in grammar . Mme. DeIassaIIe , my principal .
- Nice to meet you . - hello .
Don 't forget my rent . By check , please .
Don 't torture me . I 'm so embarrassed .
I thought of giving it to you tomorrow or the day after .
But we didn 't get paid for the examinations in Vausson .
We were counting on that money . But don 't worry ...
- I 'II come tonight . - No need . I 'II come up tomorrow .
We 're a little tired tonight .
Yes , she looks sick .
Make yourself at home .
Home , sweet home .
Turn off the light . It 's a waste .
- already ? - Let 's do it now and forget about it .
hello , operator . I 'd Iike a line to St. cloud .
The number is MoIitor 27.45 . Thank you .
I Iike to have my feet free . When it 's cold ...
I put on ski socks instead of slippers .
well , what are you waiting for ?
You see , it doesn 't bite . And it doesn 't slap either .
hello ? Who is it ? Answer , for God 's sake !
It 's you !
From Niort . My compliments !
Do you think I can afford to send you away in the Poitou ?
What about the gas ? What are you talking about ?
I 'm telling you that we need to separate .
Yes , I want a divorce .
You are young , you are strong .
You can make a nice living .
The school was part of my dowry , so I 'II take it back .
We 'II start the proceedings right after the holidays .
- What ? - Don 't give me that crap . I 'm coming .
I 'II take a train tomorrow morning .
I 'II meet you at nicole 's .
- So ? - He 's coming tomorrow on the evening train .
well , Germaine ?
You 're nuts . You 'II catch cold .
I 'm not cold . I 'm suffocating .
- You 've got fever . - No , I 'm just hot .
I thought you 'd never come back .
That he 'd get here before you .
It doesn 't always go as you want it to .
That 's life . Everything was closed .
Did you buy a tablecloth ?
Yes , a nylon , waterproof one .
- It 's too big ! - It won 't be big for him .
Guess how much ? 2500 francs .
That 's how they make money . Let 's open it .
That way it won 't look weird .
well , Iet 's not waste it .
- Here , it will cheer you up . - No .
You should , it 's not bad at all . I 've never had that before .
- You 're supposed to put water in it . - It would be a waste .
Hand me the small bottle .
- Won 't he notice anything ? - Not a thing .
He 'II sleep like a log .
- will it leave any traces ? - None .
It 's a sedative . He 'II digest it .
I 'm sure he won 't come .
That 's him . That 's his train .
Put that over there .
Stop , please , stop .
It 's awful .
- We must fill it up . - I can 't do it .
I can 't do it , not today .
We must do it , and you know it as well as I do .
- It 's either today or never . - Then never !
Let 's forget about it . I can 't handle this .
As you wish . But I must warn you .
If you miss your chance he won 't miss his .
Not after your phone call .
I don 't know . I just don 't know anymore .
nicole , please , help me .
What for ? It 's beyond your strength anyway .
I should have never trusted you .
I got involved too , and you abandoned me .
Yes , you 're right . I 'm not worth anything .
I 'm just a ruin , a little ruin .
That 's what he said . But ...
the little ruin will get her revenge . She 'II do it .
Even if she collapses afterward .
My only regret ...
is that he 'II never know that I killed him .
Come on , before you were giving up , now you 're excited .
What you need is to relax .
relax a Iot . You must keep cool .
I will . I swear that I will .
I must go upstairs and see them .
Can 't you stay with me ?
If the Herbouxes look out the window and ...
- see him come in ... - You 'II come right away , won 't you ?
As fast as I can , I promise .
Be brave , in half an hour , it will all be over .
I 'II find her a husband . I 'II redeem myself .
She 's young , she 'II be rich and she 'II be happy .
I wasn 't expecting you tonight .
Mme. DeIassaIIe is resting and I 'm not tired .
- May I come in ? - please , do .
We were listening to the radio . We 've finished eating .
The drama is over .
Zapi Max starts in a few seconds .
Dear listeners , you 've just heard ...
" One should Never Laugh at Love " by alfred de Musset .
God !
- Good evening , michel . - Good evening .
Come in .
So , are you proud of yourself ?
Not so loud , the neighbors .
Don 't worry . I don 't want to be noticed .
A man who runs after his wife is ridiculous enough .
I Ieft the school like a thief .
I had to hide from PIantiveau .
Hiding from my own doorkeeper !
It 's humiliating .
I couldn 't tell him where I was going .
You have forced me to come , what are you waiting for ?
- What ? - Pack your bags .
- No ! - What ?
- I 'm staying . - Are you refusing to come ?
I thought that was clear .
I 'II come back after our divorce .
- Have you decided to get a divorce , you ? - Yes .
With your religious beliefs ?
I won 't get married again , that 's all .
But getting a divorce is like getting married ...
we must both agree .
- My lawyer doesn 't think so . - You have a lawyer ?
- Attorney Berthoux , 64 Victor Hugo . - Berthoux ?
You can check in the phone book .
I went to see him this morning ...
and he assured me that I 'd get the legal separation quickly .
He told you that ?
Funny lawyer !
- Of course , I told him ... - You told him ...
all of our secrets ... about our private life .
You told everything to a stranger ?
An animal who enjoyed every word of it ?
You , the former nun !
I 'm telling you , it 's disgusting !
Didn 't you talk about us to your lovers ?
Do we still have secrets ?
Is there anything that nicole doesn 't know ?
Her ! If you believe her ! Two words , three lies .
There are details that she couldn 't have invented .
She can invent anything !
God knows what she told the lawyer !
- I 'II go see him , and put things straight . - No !
- You won 't stop me . - No , later . Tomorrow .
- Right now , he must be having supper - well , I didn 't eat .
- He won 't receive you . - We 'II see .
When I tell him that I came all the way from Paris ...
Don 't . I didn 't see a lawyer . I lied to you .
You too . It 's contagious .
So , what about the divorce , was that a lie too ?
No , I really want the divorce . It 's the only way .
For your sake as well , michel .
- It will be better for both of us . - Come on , Cricri .
You can 't be serious . Do you know the price of a divorce ?
- And what about the scandal ? - What scandal ?
I 'II have to take a lawyer to defend myself .
And lawyers never stop talking .
Parents won 't entrust you with their children .
- They 'II take the children away from me ? - Of course .
You 'II go bankrupt . Not that I care much .
If it were up to me , I would have sold it a Iong time ago .
With your money and my contacts I 'd have gone into business .
We could have lived comfortably .
But you wanted this kid business . I gave in .
- It was security . - Big deal !
We traded in the big car for a small one .
I gave up my training .
I used my old suits .
We are rich and we live like poor people .
Do you know how I paid for my trip ?
I sold my dictionary , my big dictionary .
And I did that for you .
believe me that I don 't regret a thing .
But when you throw me out ...
it upsets me , Cricri . It upsets me a Iot .
But anyway , you made me feel miserable .
We used to fight , Iike every other couple .
well , girls , what about this !
Wait . Don 't lie . You mustn 't lie now .
You made me very unhappy .
You might not have been aware of that , but it 's the truth .
- Ask nicole . - please , don 't talk about ...
that bitch . She 's setting you up against me .
She exploits the fact that you 're sick . She has a good mind .
Yes . She 's got knowledge , taste ...
- Taste ? - Maybe . But she doesn 't have a good mind .
That 's it . I 'm firing her right away ...
and we 'II replace her with a man . A good , honest , old man .
- michel ! - For God 's sake ! My Prince of wales suit !
You idiot ! Go get a handkerchief , a towel !
It will stain and I 'II stink of alcohol .
Just go !
Here and here .
It doesn 't pay to be nice to you .
I will break you , girl .
well , what are you waiting for ?
Bring some hot water .
We 're leaving now and we 'II be back tomorrow morning .
How long did you have to drive ? Ten , twelve hours ?
well , answer !
Can 't you talk ?
Eh , woman , another glass !
I don 't know ... I feel dizzy .
You can 't measure anymore .
That 's enough .
Nice color .
Stop looking at me with your insane eyes .
Who 's paying ? The princess ?
By the way , where is she ? Is she scared ? Hiding ?
She 's upstairs visiting the tenants .
MademoiseIIe has tenants . She never told me that .
- I 'm exhausted . It 's the train . - Just lie down .
- Whose bed is this ? Hers or yours ? - Ours .
That 's a scream .
Shoes . Take off my shoes .
What 's the matter with me tonight ?
I don 't want to sleep . I don 't want to sleep .
We have to leave .
What are you doing ?
- Just sleep . - Why did you turn off the light ?
I 'm so tired !
- What 's the matter ? - Nothing . Go to sleep .
- How did you get in ? - I came through this door .
- How many drinks did he have ? - Three .
He was very good .
He 's dreaming .
He 's ready . We can take him .
Take off his shoes .
- What the hell is she doing ? - She 's taking a bath .
At 10 P.M. ? Funny habits . Oh , shit !
tell me , sir , where are the Straits of Mozambique ?
Between Madagascar and Africa !
It is precisely located between Madagascar ...
and the Coast of Africa . Bravo , sir !
32,000 francs !
I must ask you now : what do you want to do ?
- Do you stop or do you carry on ? - I will go on .
Of course , I carry on .
I was winning 32,000 francs and I can 't hear a thing now !
- Poor baby ! - Bitches ! Bitches ! Daughters of bitches !
I didn 't even hear the question !
Midnight baths ! The decline of Rome !
It 's a problem of enjoyment !
I have the right to send her a registered letter .
And I 'm not saying that I won 't do it .
The 17th at 10 : 05 , 06 P.M.
- What are you looking for ? - His return ticket .
Here it is .
With the restaurant bill .
Burn it .
Let 's go . You take the feet . It 's lighter .
Together .
The bronze ...
The bronze on the mantel
Give it to me .
Now , the tablecloth .
The tablecloth .
It 's over .
Did he suffer too much ?
He didn 't feel anything .
Let 's go right away and bring him back tonight .
What about our alibi ?
When they find him , we 'II have to be able to prove ...
that we were here the day he died .
That 's why I 'm using the idiots upstairs .
She still hasn 't emptied the tub .
- So what ? - So I can 't go to sleep .
When she opens the drain , the noise will start again .
It won 't fall on your bed .
I can 't sleep under Niagara falls .
- Are you planning to stay up all night ? - I 'm sitting down .
I 'II give her until midnight .
- Here they are ! - They took their time .
When I passed by the cafe , at twelve ...
they were already there .
They must know how much it costs them .
- If you were a landlord , and I a school principal ... - Sure .
We could also afford good meals .
well , I 'm going to take a nap .
Here we go , the flood !
- What 's the matter ? - He 's so ugly !
I 've had it ! They must get the hell out of here !
Too bad you 're leaving us so soon .
It was so nice to have company ...
You know , school is starting tomorrow .
For us as well as for you .
I just came to take my dishes .
It 's quite heavy .
Wait a minute . would you have a piece of string ?
A piece of string ? No .
Wait . This might help you .
I 'II try , yes .
Let me do it . It 'II be easier for you .
It won 't work . Your trunk is crammed too full .
- Let 's take some things out . - No , no .
Yes . I 'II bring you the old tin trunk .
It 's very strong . It went through the 1940 retreat .
- Start emptying the basket ! - No , it 'II be fine .
- We 're already late , aren 't we , nicole ? - That 's what I told them .
Anyway , it 's fine now . We can load .
Attention ! clear the way !
On my command . One , two !
Now , it 'II be easy . A little kick in the ass .
I 'II start the engine .
- That 's it ! - As you say !
M. Herboux , thank you for your help .
- Don 't mention it . - AII the same ...
- Here , this is for the road . - Thank you , madame .
Drive carefully , the roads are dangerous .
They have mobilized 1500 policemen .
You 'II find one at every crossroad .
Goodbye , madame . And thank you again .
- Have a good trip . - See you soon !
It won 't be this time .
- A little bit earlier , or later . - Great ...
There is only one possible end .
We are monsters . I don 't like monsters .
If it 's only him , I feel better . Because ...
the grain of sand falling off the hands of providence ...
I 'II keep that for my Sunday school lesson .
well , don 't stop !
It is about time ! AII the gas stations were empty !
No wonder ! It was crazy today .
Wait . There is always some left in the bottom .
- 963 francs . - I only have a 5,000 franc bill .
Come with me . I 'II get some change .
- Are you going to Tours ? - No , I 'm not .
could you give me a lift ?
The bus driver wouldn 't take me .
He 's anti-miIitarist , Iike me .
We are already two . Can 't you see there 's no room ?
I won 't take room . A second class soldier .
If I don 't report , they 'II put me in jail .
Have some pity for a soldier .
Leave me alone . You 're drunk .
Me ? Hey you !
I 'm being polite . And if that 's the way it is ...
I 'II just get into your car .
I won 't let you . Do you hear me ?
nicole ! would you get out !
- What is it ? - Don 't worry .
He 's drunk . I know him . He 's not a bad guy .
You should be ashamed of yourself , Robert .
Get out of here , or I 'II push you out myself .
The pig . What did he do ?
The floor is all wet . I 'II clean it .
No , no need . We 're in a hurry . Thank you .
Start the car . There 's a hole in the nylon !
- Did you hear that ? - It sounds like the boss .
- He decided to come back . - It 's about time !
Is this the time to make all this racket ?
If we only ring , PIantiveau won 't open .
Three short strokes , that 's michel 's signal .
PIantiveau is a heavy sleeper .
I 'II wake him up myself !
- Come on PIantiveau ! - It 's you ?
I thought it was M. DeIassaIIe .
What ? Isn 't he here ?
Do I know ? Ask him when you see him .
- You look tired . - Are you surprised ?
You can go .
- Sorry to have awakened you . Good night - Good night .
Turn off the light . For our number ...
- we don 't need spotlights . - No music either !
Oh , not now .
- That 's the bathroom light - It 's PascuaI .
I heard he gets up every night .
He might be able to look out the window .
- Can we see him from here ? - No .
Either the water is too dirty , or we 're too far away .
I 'm telling you that we can 't see anything .
What 's the point in staying here ?
We 're not supposed to discover the body .
- close the window . It 's freezing . - Shut up . It stinks in here .
Good news . The principal didn 't come back .
- He 's in heat . - He 's already got two chicks . Isn 't that enough ?
Of course , not . When I grow up , I 'II have a Iot .
Look at napoleon and Louis XIV .
AII the big men used to have a Iot of chicks .
- Do you think you 're napoleon ? - I 'm falcon Eye .
M. Moinet , stop playing the fool .
I 'm not a fool . I am an Indian .
Then you can write : " My absurd comments provoke ...
" my friends ' hilarity " , 20 times .
What do I hear ? The principal is missing ?
This is the third time , dear friend ...
that I drink my wine , chemically pure .
Where is he ? I saw him the day before yesterday ...
around eight o 'cIock . By twelve , he was already gone .
And he didn 't show up again ?
That 's not Iike him .
Poor Mme. DeIassaIIe . She has enough troubles already .
If she 's no more worried than I am , he can stay where he is .
But believe me , he 'II be back soon .
And we 'II start drinking bad wine again .
Did you notice ? This afternoon ...
it seemed that he pretended not to see the body .
The body was at the bottom .
- Do you think it will rise ? - It has to .
- When ? - How should I know ?
- Tonight . Tomorrow morning . - It makes me nervous .
We cannot ask to empty the pool . Try to understand .
It 's natural to empty a pool when the water is dirty .
What we find inside won 't be natural at all .
I 'II take the responsibility for this .
In order to take responsibilities , you have to be an adult .
You think like a child .
You 're not worth anything .
How can you grade papers ?
By mistake I just wrote complete nonsense
- well , erase it . - I don 't have an eraser .
If his body doesn 't come up by tomorrow ...
I 'II manage to have the pool emptied .
And I hope we won 't regret it .
Don 't bite your nails .
I was not in the game .
- Look ! - I was expecting that .
Don 't bring attention to it .
- I told you not to look . - Do something !
My heart is about to explode . You promised yesterday .
Give me the keys . We 'II move things faster .
That was clever . Go and bring the pole .
Me ! Me ! Me !
Soudieu ! Let 's test you on a 100 meters .
As for you , you need some training in the shot put .
You 're lucky . You have a champion skin diver here .
- Soudieu ! I forbid you ! - Let him ! He 's a champion !
What 's happening ? It 's taking him too long .
He might be drowning . Did you see the bubbles ?
Did you get them ? Say something !
I found it . It was shining in the mud .
It looks like M. DeIassaIIe 's lighter .
- And you didn 't see ... - The keys !
It 's chocolate soup at the bottom .
Go get dressed . Don 't catch cold . We 'II manage .
I think we 'II have to empty the pool .
You 're right . Send PIantiveau over .
What are you waiting for ?
PIantiveau ...
It 's deep where you 're standing .
- It 's all right . I can swim . - So what ?
A Iot of people who can swim drown .
Because the ones who can 't stay away from the edge .
- I want you to empty the pool . - Right now ?
I 'm not dressed for it . I was going to the barber .
Do it now , PIantiveau . It 's urgent .
- Do it for me . - AII right . The fish will wait .
only to empty the pool will take an hour .
She 's upset . Be cool .
Why are you staring at me ? Is something wrong with me ?
Again . The surface of a hexagon ...
in relation to the radius of the circumference ?
well , I 'm waiting .
I 'm waiting ...
- 6 AB x 1 / 2 OH . - Thank you . Good . Go back to your seat .
Take out your notebooks .
Wait a minute . I 'II be back soon .
M. PIantiveau !
What happened to her ?
It can 't be true . It 's impossible !
- I didn 't see well ! - You saw very well !
- He isn 't there anymore ? - No , he isn 't .
- Come in . What is it ? - It 's the doctor , mademoiselle .
I think it comes from the open space , the empty pool .
She suffers from agoraphobia , and she got dizzy .
- It 's possible . - Nature abhors a vacuum .
An empty pool isn 't worth a full bottle , PIantiveau .
Is she feeling any better , dear colleague ?
Dr. Loisy is with her .
You 'II take her pupils for study hall , M. Raymond ...
and you , M. Drain , watch my class for a few minutes .
Mme. DeIassaIIe might still need me .
Of course . Did you notice ? She gives orders now .
- So , doctor ? - That 's what we should all expect .
When it 's used , it 's used . Where is the husband ?
He should come here fast .
In the meantime , no emotions , no vexations . Spare her .
Don 't you think a specialist ...
If you want , I 'II call Bridoux .
He 's 60 years old , but he 's got the best ear in Paris ...
and he 's the finest gourmet ! For him a meal is a meal .
Anyway , give her some digitaIis .
- The doctor said ... - I don 't care . close the shutters and go .
No . It would be too easy . Much too easy .
Does a corpse that disappears seem natural to you ? Not to me .
If he 's not in the pool , someone took him out .
I asked PIantiveau if he opened the door for anyone .
- He said no one . - Why would he lie ?
If no one went out ...
the body should be around here . I 've searched everywhere .
The attic , the basements , the garden . There 's nothing .
No dirt , no footsteps . There 's nothing .
My head is about to explode . It 's crazy .
It 's been crazy since the beginning .
Not even a kid 's game .
You took one of your word problems
with leaking taps , and tanks that empty ...
and you planned a murder from it .
In real life , this kind of thing does not exist .
Bathtubs that we fill up , swimming pools that we empty .
That was crazy . And I was crazy to listen to you .
Come in !
Somebody brought back monsieur 's suit .
The one he 's been wearing lately .
- The Prince of wales . - Who brought it back ?
- The dry-cIeaner . - What dry-cIeaner ?
I don 't know . He came on a bicycle .
He looked at the street name ...
and asked again if it was the right address .
A very conscientious little guy .
Get to the point .
He said it was from M. DeIassaIIe .
So I asked him : " Did you see M. DeIassaIIe ? Where ? "
So he said : " I didn 't see him " ...
but he asked me to bring the suit home , urgently .
well , should I hang it up in the closet ?
No . Leave it here .
It is his suit .
That 's completely insane !
Wait .
Rue St. Ferdinand .
- Good morning . - Excuse me .
Did you deliver a suit this morning in St. cloud ?
- What 's the name ? - Mme . DeIassaIIe .
- Was there a problem ? - No . We just want to know who ...
- brought this suit to you . - We see so many of them !
If I remember well , it was a tall thin man , dark hair ...
with a bamboo cigarette holder .
There 's a check mark . The kid forgot something .
It was in his pocket .
Eden hotel . Room nine .
Your husband seems to be leading some life !
I can have the kid bring the key , if you wish .
Do you know this hotel , madam ?
It 's a residential hotel . Very cozy .
Come on !
First street on the right . Number 27 .
- I 'II go . - What if they ask you something ?
It looks like they don 't ask questions here .
Don 't go , it 's a trap . Someone wants to blackmail us .
At least , we 'II know with whom we are dealing .
- What are you doing here ? - I 'm looking for M. DeIassaIIe .
He 's never here during the day .
- When does he come back ? - Who knows if he comes back at all .
His bed is always neat . See , no belongings , no bags .
Nothing . Some weird guest .
Did you ever see him ?
Never , neither did the doorkeeper .
He must come , after I leave ...
and before the other guy starts his shift .
But , why all these questions ?
He 's my husband . I am Mme. DeIassaIIe .
Poor lady ! This isn 't where you should look for him .
You can trust me . His life is somewhere else .
It 's scary . What 's happening to us ?
I don 't know . No one knows .
It doesn 't make any sense .
80,000 francs . Shower repair , and it 's two years old .
Ah , this time it smells the bailiff .
Pay them half . It 's already something .
- He was really dead , wasn 't he ? - You 're the one who should know .
- Why are you saying that ? - You killed him , didn 't you ?
- Me ? - You are the one who planned the whole thing .
I 'm sorry , we planned it ...
and you made the phone call .
You bought the tablecloth to wrap him ...
the drug to put him to sleep .
I would have been unable to do that .
- But you made him drink ! - You liar ! I didn 't want to !
You know I didn 't want to !
You could 've let him sleep his whiskey off ...
instead of carrying him to the tub .
Who filled up the tub ? Who pushed him under water ?
And who brought the bronze from the mantel ?
It 's too easy .
You 'II see whom the court will hold responsible .
- You 'II see . - The court doesn 't scare me .
We 'II get what we deserve .
well , suit yourself ! Go to the police ! Go !
- I thought of that . - To put the whole thing on me !
I won 't let this happen . I 'II call the cops first !
call them , but I 'm warning you , I 'II tell them everything !
I have nothing to hide . You were jealous , and killed him .
And I helped you because I felt pity for you .
You were jealous because it was over between you two .
You killed him , and you know it !
So , what are you waiting for ?
- Do you have my newspapers ? - Yes .
Be careful not to get dirty . The ink is still wet .
- Christina ! - I have nothing to tell you .
- Where are you going ? - To confession . Do you mind ?
Do you think you 'II get absolution if you don 't turn yourself in ?
- So I 'II turn myself in . - What about me ?
I can 't keep this up .
Come on , don 't worry . It 's all over .
They found the body . Read this .
" A Naked Corpse in the Seine "
- Why in the Seine ? - What counts is that they found him .
Everything fits . The description ...
The Bois de boulogne bridge which is very close ...
a three day old death . Our alibi is holding up .
They brought him to the morgue .
I read this , and I think it 's my husband .
Identity card .
could you describe M. DeIassaIIe ?
Dark hair , thin , dark eyes .
AII this has already been written in the paper . It 's too easy .
- I want details . - What do you want to know ?
I don 't know . You tell me .
If you tell me he had an appendectomy ...
- it 's a detail . - He 's had the operation .
- Dentition . How many teeth ? - AII of them , I think .
- fillings ? - Maybe one or two .
- One or two ? - Two .
- Beauty marks ? - Yes .
- Where ? - On his shoulder .
Why didn 't you tell me he had a bracelet ?
- He never had one ! - really !
- What do you see on his right thigh ? - Nothing .
Try to think , above the knee .
I can 't see anything . So it must be a mistake .
Bring up number 4702 . You were right .
No bracelet and nothing above the knee .
please , follow me to the identification room .
- It 's not him . - Are you sure ?
- Yes ! - I 'm sorry , madame . This rarely happens .
Taxi ! To St. cloud !
St. cloud ? Now ? Are you out of your mind ?
I don 't want to have supper on a merry-go-round !
Excuse me ...
Here we go !
Aren 't you feeling well , lady ? Maybe it 's the emotion .
The reaction only comes after , doesn 't it ?
You should feel better since it 's not him .
Drive .
Do you feel better ? Let me introduce myself .
alfred Fichet , retired police commissioner .
But I didn 't ask the police for anything !
Didn 't you inform the police commissioner ?
It was a mistake . That 's what they are for .
I didn 't think about it . I 'II do it .
I 'II do it myself . Just out of principle .
One should not expect too much from the regular police .
The police are too busy .
No . If you 'd Iike , we are both going to find your husband .
40 years on the job , it 's not to be ignored .
Now , I have plenty of time .
- No . really , it 's not necessary . - What do you risk ?
If I don 't find anything , you won 't pay me anything .
And if I find something ... well , you 'II judge for yourself .
You can 't ask for a better deal . Let 's see .
- You 've been married ... - Eight years .
- I don 't understand what ... - Leave it to me . I know .
We are saying eight years .
It 's boiling , mademoiselle .
- How long do you think it can boil ? - Five minutes .
How do I know . He had his own keys .
He would go in , and out . He was the boss .
And it was vacation anyway .
- Was he a little Iow-spirited ? - It was not his style .
It was more in his nature to complicate his life .
- Maybe he was feeling sick . - CouIdn 't be .
The man was very strong .
When he was younger , he was a tennis champion .
Did he get a telegram on Sunday ?
A phone call ? Sometimes , people leave after a phone call .
I can 't tell you , sir .
This Sunday I took my wife to the park ...
and when the school is closed , we seize the opportunity .
There might be the hypothesis of the accident .
Did M. DeIassaIIe used to drive fast , very fast ?
He didn 't have the car . The women took it to Niort .
That 's right . Don 't you think he could 've drowned ?
Drowned ? He was a real fish .
This man could swim .
I see . well , thank you .
The alps separate italy from France in the southeast .
The alps are very high mountains .
There is Mont-BIanc , the highest mountain in Europe .
In the east , there is the Jura ...
That is quite reassuring .
I think you worried a little bit too early .
On Saturday , your husband was still here .
It 's only been five days , and you go look for him at the morgue .
The article in the paper upset me .
A 30 year old man , one meter seventy ...
Dear madame , there are 100,000 men in Paris who fit ...
this description . And this doesn 't include the tourists .
I guess you were thinking of suicide .
Yes . well , I don 't know .
To commit suicide in the Seine , one doesn 't need to undress .
My hypothesis is much less tragic .
When I say hypothesis , I mean ...
A woman ! Of course , you 're right .
I was stupid to worry and to bother you .
- Take this . - No , no . I won 't steal your money .
Remember our agreement .
If I don 't find out anything , you don 't owe me anything .
But , don 't worry , I 'II find him .
I haven 't been in a school for a Iong time .
In my days , it was the local school . Charonne .
Less fancy . Much less fancy .
Ah , it was really different .
You emptied the pool . You thought about this too .
- Not at all ! - Why not at all ?
I dropped my keys in the pool .
- So in order to get them back ... - When was that ?
- Yesterday . - Commissioner Fichet . mile . Horner .
- Our most devoted associate . - hello .
It was pure coincidence .
really , the keys in the pool , the husband in the morgue ...
You dream too much about water in this house !
May I Iook at his mail ?
- You 'II never find him . - How do you know anyway ?
- I see he has a typewriter . - Yes , for the accounts .
You 're right . M. DeIassaIIe is not a literary man .
Perhaps he doesn 't trust his spelling .
May I ? I seriously can 't imagine him that desperate .
Let 's take this seriously .
So we 're saying : DeIassaIIe michel ...
- 34 years old ... - One meter seventy .
- Yes , I know . Dark hair . Eyes ? - Brown .
Average nose , ears ... folded in .
How to find someone with this description ?
well , we 'II find him . These pigs are so strong !
What was he wearing the day he disappeared ?
We were away that day , sir .
Of course ! How stupid of me .
Here 's what we 'II do .
We 'II look into his wardrobe ...
and we 'II see what is missing .
One , two , three , four , five , six . Six .
- What did the 7th pair look like ? - Brown suede .
- Tie ? - Red , with a white stripe .
You 're sharp-eyed . He 's got at Ieast 25 ties .
So , suit ?
Suit !
So you know his ties better than his suits .
I think it 's a Prince of wales , grey .
Prince of wales , grey .
- Like this one ? - Yes .
- Wait a minute . - Is something wrong ?
Mme. DeIassaIIe has a heart condition . We must spare her .
You should have told me .
It 's not that urgent . I 've got enough to keep myself busy .
Take care of yourself .
I 'II go visit downtown .
I still have friends there .
And don 't worry . I 'II be back .
- PIantiveau said he 's a detective . - A private one .
Everybody to the firing squad !
Heberge , if you 're done with your work ...
I 'II find something else for you to do .
First , Latin . When the middle Ages lost everything ...
they still knew Latin . The Church understood it .
The last village priest knew Latin .
I don 't think that the average priest ...
is that clever .
It 's not his job .
M. Moinet , what are you doing here ?
Aren 't you supposed to be studying ?
- The principal punished me . - Who ?
- The principal . - What are you talking about ?
- It 's the truth . - What did you do ?
I broke a window .
Maybe the principal came back .
Stop talking nonsense . tell me the truth , now .
- Who punished you ? - The principal .
- That 's for lying ! - I 'm not lying .
Let me handle this . You 're scaring him .
tell me your story again .
And if you tell everything , I 'II lift your punishment .
- How did you break the window ? - With my slingshot .
- Then what happened ? - The principal opened the door ...
and told me to go to bed right away ...
without picking up the dead leaves .
It can 't be him . It 's impossible .
You know he 's not here .
You forget that this kid is a pathological liar .
Last week , he told his friends he had a fight ...
with a lion at the fair . With a lion !
He 's a mythomaniac . I just asked the other kids .
Nobody saw the principal .
But there really is a broken window in the corridor .
He punished himself in order to create this story .
Who knows ? obviously ...
this is a case of seIf-induced hallucination .
The kid broke a window and in his subconscious ...
he generated the idea of punishment ...
to match the principal 's .
Darkness did the rest .
- Do you really think so ? - No . The kid saw himself ...
being punished in the literal sense of the word .
I think he 's kidding us ...
in the literal sense of the word .
- Give me your slingshot . - The principal took it .
Don 't you think you 're a little out of line ?
I feel tired . I 'm going to sleep .
- Suit yourself . - Goodnight .
Goodnight . Go get some rest .
M. Moinet . We 've been patient enough .
If you want to be stubborn ...
go straight to the corner .
You 'II get out only after you tell the truth .
We 'II see who gets tired first .
I saw him . I saw him .
- Moinet couldn 't have brought this slingshot . - certainly not .
- So who could 've done that ? - It could be anyone .
- It 's a coincidence . - Coincidence !
Fichet at the morgue , was a coincidence .
And the suit , and the hotel , and now the students .
Is it a coincidence that it 's getting closer each time ?
please , calm down . My nerves are going as well .
It 's all getting clear . There are no miracles in life .
unfortunately .
Each time I close my eyes ...
it seems that I 'm going to see him .
Don 't talk . He must already be in some condition .
Yes , if he 's dead .
Listen , I 've seen dead people in my Iife .
believe me , michel is dead . really dead .
Lie down and try not to think of anything .
With all I have on my mind ...
If you don 't get any sleep , you won 't last three days .
Dr. Loisy is very worried .
He asked Prof. Bridoux to come tomorrow .
There you are !
What 's the point now ? I 'm finished .
- Stop that . - Give me back my marbles .
- I don 't have them . - You took them , I know .
- I 'm going to break your neck ! - Leave me alone !
- Give him back his marbles . - Leave me alone .
- I haven 't got them . Stop it ! - Come on , come on !
You can fight , but don 't scream . Mme. DeIassaIIe is very sick .
Moinet , your punishment is lifted ... for now .
- Go for your picture . - Thank you , sir .
A picture without the principals , is not a school picture .
We 'II do better next year . Come on , children .
Do we put the bench in front of the window ?
- Why not in front of the door ? - What about the car ?
There is a professor from the university upstairs .
I must go . It 's part of the job .
I 'II show the professor out , and I 'II call you .
You overdid it .
You should really have a good rest .
- will I be able to get up ? - We 'II talk about this later .
- You will be fine here . - could I go out into the yard ?
- Is it too much for me ? - until the doctors say so ...
you are not supposed to move .
Let 's do it . Look at my hand . Don 't move .
One , two . Thank you . One minute . I 'II take another one .
You can go through .
Taking her to my clinic would have been too expensive .
Between you and me , there are no heirs .
I know . But people dying in the clinic ...
the hearse in front of the door , I don 't like that .
Neither do the patients .
- Let me see ! - Be careful , kids . It 's still wet .
Great . Nobody moved .
please ... I came out fine .
This is the first time I 've had the position of honor .
When I show the picture , they 'II think I 'm the principal .
- What do I see behind the window ? - Looks like the boss .
- You 're nuts ! - Wait ! Let me put my monocle on .
- Let me see , mademoiselle ! - Leave me alone !
- I didn 't see anything ? ! - You didn 't miss anything .
It 's some kind of shot-siIk effect .
The reflection of a cloud or some spot on the window ...
that reminds us of the principal 's features .
Maybe it 's him !
He didn 't want to interrupt us ...
or this was just an innocent joke .
I can 't see DeIassaIIe playing hide-and-seek .
But you , didn 't you see anything ?
I was looking at the group , being sure to see everybody .
Let 's settle this once and for all . Moinet .
You 're such a great observer . Did you see the principal ?
Six hours in the corner , thank you , that 's enough !
The case is closed . There wasn 't anyone .
thankfully . really . To hear people saying ...
that people go in and out of here ...
without me knowing it , it 's offensive for a doorkeeper .
- I 'm afraid . - Me too .
We must go now . Here , get dressed !
The doctors forbid me to move . Where would we go , anyway ?
To my place .
In Niort ? Don 't you think he might be there as well ?
He 's more certainly there , than anywhere else .
So , we 'II travel , we 'II go anywhere .
It 's not possible . There 's no point .
- I can 't stay here anymore . - So , just go .
What about you ? I can 't leave you here .
Yes . You 'II see . And you 'II get used to managing without me .
Besides , I don 't want to see you anymore .
For all that 's about to happen ...
for all that will eventually happen ...
I 'd rather be on my own .
No , no , please !
- You hate me , don 't you ? - Not at all .
Where is the little red suitcase I gave you ?
On the floor , by the closet .
So you really think it 's time for us to separate ?
Yes , it 'II be better that way .
- I hope you succeed and forget . - farewell , Christina .
" tremble , she told me , a girl worthy of me .
" The cruel God of the Jews is stronger than you .
" I pity you for failing in his fearsome hands . "
- What are you doing here ? - I was just looking at you .
I came to make my report . That 's what I 'm paid for .
But you were sleeping so deeply ...
Leave me alone . I 'm sick , very sick .
You 'II feel better very soon .
Everything is fine .
Can 't you have some pity for me and let me die alone ?
Do you think I 'm not dying fast enough ?
What 's the matter with you ?
It 's not the time to die .
I found him . He 'II be here very shortly .
It 's wrong , and you know it .
You know he can 't come back .
- Why ? - Because I killed him .
- This afternoon ? - Five days ago .
Five ... So we mustn 't be talking about the same one .
- Five days ago in Niort . - And you went to the morgue ?
- His body disappeared . - From Niort ?
No , from here ! We brought him back in the truck ...
in a wicker trunk .
When we got here , we threw him in the swimming pool .
But you weren 't alone in Niort .
- You were with mademoiselle ... - Horner .
Horner , yes . And didn 't she notice anything ?
She was his mistress . She helped me . - I see .
She was his mistress ...
and she helped you . well ...
I wouldn 't mind listening to what she 's got to say .
- She got scared , and she left . - It was obvious ...
It won 't work . It 's michel 's .
It was under water a whole day .
well , well ...
Aren 't you arresting me ?
You should stop playing with your nerves .
You need a strong sedative .
Goodnight .
shall I turn off the light ?
Tomorrow morning , you 'II wake up acquitted .
He disappeared . She 's deficient .
In addition , nicole runs away .
- Doesn 't it remind you of anything ? - Registering for unemployment .
I 'm afraid . Here 's the cop .
I found it under the diving board .
- Isn 't there a wicker trunk around here ? - Yes , sir .
- Above the garage . - So , Iet 's go .
It 's starting to stink .
You wonder if anything happened to DeIassaIIe .
You 're a witness that I didn 't know anything .
Me either , dear colleague .
Right . Let him manage alone .
I don 't know why , but ...
You think that we fucked up . Me too .
M. Pacard . Moinet .
- Goodnight , sir . - Goodnight .
Who 's there ?
It 's over , this time .
She 's was tough .
The bitch . She used to say that she had a heart condition .
My poor darling . You 're all wet .
Go change your clothes .
In the bathroom , it took me ...
more than one hour to get out of the tub without making noise .
You must 've suffered during the trip in the trunk .
What about the dive in the pool in the middle of the night ?
She made life terrible for us .
I got scared more than four times .
Wasn 't it worth it ?
Now , we 're rich .
Just by selling the school , we 'II get a Iot ...
Between 15 and 20 years in jail .
It 'II depend on the judge .
Moinet , Moinet .
Wait a moment .
You again , Moinet . You should be ashamed of yourself .
On the day we 're closing the school .
- Who gave you this slingshot ? - Mme . DeIassaIIe .
- Who ? - Mme . DeIassaIIe . She opened her door .
She gave me back my slingshot .
She said : " This is for you , Moinet . Have fun . "
You are impossible . You know that she 's dead .
- Her body was taken away today . - She 's not dead . She came back .
M. Moinet , go to the corner .
I saw her . I know that I saw her .
Don 't be devils . Don 't ruin ...
the interest your friends could take in this film .
Don 't tell them what you saw .
Thank you for them .